Finding aid for Library (University of Michigan) Records, 1837 - 2013
Bentley Historical Library
Library (University of Michigan) records
1837 - 2013
1920 - 2000
Bentley Historical Library
University of Michigan. Library.
87239 BImu Bimu C410 2 UBImum C410 2
297.3 linear feet
1 oversize volume
1 oversize folder
The University Library system at the University of Michigan provides information resources and services to faculty, students, staff, and the public, and is comprised of undergraduate, graduate, and subject-oriented divisional collections. The record group includes administrative files of library directors, reports, committee files, financial records, photographs, and publications.
The records of the library (Donor No. 1278 ) have been received in various installments. Periodic additions are expected.
The University of Michigan Library records are open for research except for certain records restricted by statute or university policy. Restricted material includes personnel-related files, including search, review, promotion, and tenure files; student educational records; client/patient records; and records of executive officers of the university.
The University of Michigan Library record group includes restricted material in the following categories:
Personnel Related Records -- Boxes 250, 290
Student Academic Records -- Box 250
Executive Officer Records -- Boxes 267, 272-273, 275-276, 294-295, 297-298, oversize folder 1
Access Restrictions for University of Michigan Records
University records are public records and once fully processed are generally open to research use. Records that contain personally identifiable information will be restricted in order to protect individual privacy. Certain administrative records are restricted in accordance with university policy as outlined below. The restriction of university records is subject to compliance with applicable laws, including the Michigan Freedom of Information Act.
Categories of Restricted Records
Personnel-related files, including search, review, promotion, and tenure files, are restricted for thirty (30) years from the date of their creation.
Student educational records: FERPA's protection of personally identifiable information in a student's education records ends at the time of a student's death and therefore is a matter of institutional policy. As a courtesy to the families of recently deceased students who were enrolled at the time of death, the University generally will not release information from their education records for five years without the consent of the deceased student's next of kin. Eighty-five (85) years after the date the records were first created, the University will presume that the student is deceased. Thereafter the student's education records will be open. Student records at the Bentley Historical Library are restricted for eighty-five (85) years, but may also be made available upon proof of the death of the student.
Executive records: Records generated by the university's executive officers, deans, directors, department heads, and their designated support staff are restricted for twenty (20) years from the date of their creation.
Restricted files are indicated in the contents list of the collection’s finding aid with a restriction note indicating the restriction type and the date of expiration.
For further information on the restriction policy and placing Freedom of Information Act requests for restricted material, consult the reference archivist at the Bentley Historical Library (bentley.ref@umich.edu) or the University of Michigan Freedom of Information Office website (https://foia.vpcomm.umich.edu/).
The University Library system provides information resources and services to faculty, students, staff, and the public, and is comprised of undergraduate, graduate, and subject-oriented divisional collections. The library holds over seven million volumes and a wide variety of cartographic, audiovisual, manuscript, microform, and digital materials.
(Please note that some of the libraries at the University of Michigan are not part of the University Library system. These include the Law Library, the Kresge Business Administration Library, the Gerald R. Ford Presidential Library, the Clements Library, and the Bentley Historical Library. Individual findings aids for the record groups of most of these libraries can be found at the Bentley Library.)
The Library has long played a central role in the development of the University. The Act of 1837, which provided for the organization of the university, included a provision stating that a portion of student fees would go toward increasing the library. The Board of Regents elected Reverend Henry Colclazer to serve as librarian. A year later, in September 1838, the Regents passed a resolution authorizing Asa Gray, Professor of Botany and Zoology, to purchase the materials to serve as the basis for the library's collection while on a tour of Europe, and appropriated $5000 for this purpose. While in London, Gray commissioned George Palmer Putnam to select most of the materials, developing a collection of 3,401 volumes covering the subjects of history, philosophy, literature, science, the arts, and law. The complete list of titles was printed as a state document in 1841. The Library is unusual in that, unlike most academic libraries, it was established through a major purchase rather than a gift.
In November 1841, the Regents approved the Regulations for the Library which included that the library would be open once a week, no books be loaned to students without faculty approval, that fines were to be paid for overdue books, and that no more than two volumes could be borrowed at a time. Initially housed in the home of one of the university's professors, the books were moved to the third floor of the Main Building in December 1841.
In 1854, President Henry Tappan initiated a subscription drive among Ann Arbor residents to raise funds for acquisitions and called for an annual appropriation from the Regents. These acts brought a steady infusion of money to ensure ongoing collection development. After years of having a succession of faculty members serve annual terms as the librarian, Tappan's son, John L. Tappan, was appointed as full-time librarian in 1856, and effectively became the first Librarian of the University.
As the Library's collections grew, it outgrew the space afforded it. After a series of shared homes, including spaces in the North University Building and the Law Building, the state legislature appropriated $100,000 for the library to have its own purpose-built building (1881). Opened in 1883 and located in the center of campus, the library consisted of a large reading room attached to cruciform stacks. When the library outgrew that space and several additions, the university secured over $350,000 from the legislature for a new building to be designed by Albert Kahn (1915). The existing library was demolished, and a new General Library building opened in 1920. Several divisional libraries, including collections devoted to rare books, natural science, chemical engineering, education, and museums were also established during this time period. Some of these collections were housed within the General Library while others were hosted out of academic departments or other buildings on campus.
Over the years the directors of the University Library made a number of important contributions to the development of the library and the larger field of library and information science. Andrew Ten Brook (1864 - 1877) introduced the library's first card catalog, with handwritten author and subject cards for both books and periodical articles. Raymond C. Davis (1877 - 1905) directed increased collection development and oversaw the opening of the first General Library building. Theodore W. Koch (1905 -1915) developed the library's first reference collection and instituted a library orientation program. William Warner Bishop (1915 - 1941), nationally recognized as one of the country's leading librarians, presided over the establishment of the Library Extension Service, the opening of the new General Library in 1920, the development of substantial divisional and specialized collections, and a number of cataloging innovations, in addition to leading the university's first Department of Library Science and serving terms as the presidents of the American Library Association (ALA) and the International Federation of Library Associations (IFLA).
In the 1950s and 1960s, the way in which the library provided services to the academic community evolved. Whereas once the General Library had served as the major research center for all academic subjects on campus, as the university's academic programs expanded and the need for collections to support those programs grew, the General Library's role came to be seen more as providing support solely for the humanities and social sciences. Specialized divisional libraries and libraries that provided services targeted to particular groups of patrons began to grow to support all other subjects. Rather than conceiving of them as small collections that supplemented the General Library, the library began developing larger and more self-contained divisional libraries, including the Physics-Astronomy Library, the first divisional library to be purpose-built rather than housed in a building designed for other purposes. As the network of campus libraries grew larger, the entire system came to be known as the University Library system.
The most important new library built in this time period was the Undergraduate Library, which opened in 1958. Designed to house a select collection of standard works commonly consulted by undergraduate students, the Undergraduate Library was the first large open-stack library on campus, though many of the divisional libraries already had open stacks. The Undergraduate Library differed from other libraries on campus in that it contained space for students to read, listen to recordings, and meet with others, as well as reference services specifically geared to undergraduate students. Open stacks were subsequently introduced in the General Library. These innovations led to increased library use and circulation on campus.
A seven-level addition to the General Library was constructed in 1970. The new addition nearly doubled the General Library's capacity, and provided added space for users and staff. While originally only the South Building was to be given a new name, soon after its opening the entire complex housing the North and South Buildings came to be called the Harlan Hatcher Graduate Library. New divisional libraries were also constructed in the 1970s and 1980s, most notably the Taubman Medical Library in 1979.
In the 1970s, the University Library system began a program of automated cataloging through the Michigan Library Consortium. Automation became fully integrated into library operations in August 1988, when the library's online catalog MIRLYN (Michigan Research Library Network) was introduced. The retrospective conversion of card catalog data was funded by the W.K. Kellogg Foundation and included over 10 million bibliographic records, covering 99% of the library's collections.
The University Library continued to grow in the 1990s and 2000s. One of the most significant developments during the decade was the establishment of the library's Digital Library Services in 1993, which develops and maintains digital resources to support research and instruction and provides technology management services for the University Library system. Another important accomplishment was the library's participation in the campus-wide initiative led by President James Duderstadt to design the Media Union on North Campus. Opened in 1996, the Media Union houses the Art and Architecture and Engineering Libraries, and hosts and provides services for an extensive array of innovative digital tools and resources. Under the leadership of Paul Courant (University Librarian from 2007-2013), the University Library expanded its digital collections through its participation in the Google digitization project (an ambitious initiative to digitize all the books in the library) and the creation of HathiTrust Shared Digital Repository.
The University Library continues to be one of the leading research libraries in the world, with innovative programs in digital library services, access, and reference, and nearly unparalleled depth and breadth of collections.
Directors of the University Libraries
1856-1864 John L. Tappan
1864-1877 Andrew Ten Brook
1877-1905 Raymond C. Davis
1905-1915 Theodore W. Koch
1915-1941 William Warner Bishop
1941-1953 Warner G. Rice
1953-1978 Frederick H. Wagman
1978-1985 Richard Dougherty
1985-1990 Robert M. Warner
1991-1996 Donald Riggs
1997-1998 William A. Gosling (Interim)
1998-2005 William A. Gosling
2007-2013 Paul Courant
2013- James L. Hilton
The physical arrangement of the records reflects the various accession in which the material was received. In this finding aid the intellectual structure of the records is given priority -- like material from different accessions is brought together with the result that in the detailed contents list box numbers may not be in consecutive order.
The records of the library of the University of Michigan document the development and administration of the central library. The records include topical files, miscellaneous correspondence and reports, and business record books, 1886-1916; include files of librarians/directors/deans Theodore W. Koch, William W. Bishop, Warner G. Rice, Frederick H. Wagman, Richard Dougherty, Robert M. Warner, Don Riggs, William A. Gosling, and Paul Courant; also assorted papers of earlier librarians, Andrew Ten Brook and Raymond C. Davis.
The records are organized into elleven subgroups:
Assistant Director for Technical Services, 1984 - 1999
Associate Director for Public Service Files, 1976 - 1998
Associate Director for Technical Services, 1979 - 1986
Associate Director's office, 1982 - 1989
Audio - Visual Materials, 1954 - 2001
Collection Development Office, 1949 - 1986
Deputy Director's Office, 1980 - 1991
Directors Office, 1905-2013
Human Resources, 1956 - 2001
Miscellaneous Records, 1837 - 1985
Other Offices and Programs, 1904 - 2004
Interiors.; Libraries -- Michigan -- Ann Arbor.; Libraries -- Michigan -- Interlochen.; Microphotography.; Pornography.; Photographs.; Photonegatives.; American Library Association.; Association of College and Research Libraries.; Bodleian Library.; Association of Research Libraries.; Biblioteca Apostolica Vaticana.; Council on Library Resources.; Library of Congress.; Michigan Library Association.; National Library of Medicine (U.S.); Projected Books, inc.; University of Michigan. Library.; United States. Commission on Obscenity and Pornography.; United States. National Advisory Commission on Libraries.; University of Michigan -- Buildings.; University of Michigan -- Faculty.; University of Michigan. Library.; Interlochen Center for the Arts.; University of Michigan. Library.; University of Michigan. School of Information and Library Studies.; Angell, James Burrill, 1829-1916.; Bishop, William Warner, 1871-1955.; Bowker, R. R. (Richard Rogers), 1848-1933.; Burton, Clarence Monroe, 1853-1932.; Burton, Marion Le Roy, 1874-1925.; Casey, Genevieve M., 1916-; Clements, William L. (William Lawrence), 1861-1934.; Courant, Paul.; Dana, John Cotton, 1856-1929.; Davis, R. C. (Raymond Cazallis), 1836-; Dougherty, Richard M.; Frankhauser, Mary E.; Fyan, Loleta D.; Goodrich, Francis Lee Dewey, 1877-1962.; Gosling, William A.; Hubbard, Lucius L. (Lucius Lee), 1849-1933.; Hutchins, Harry B. (Harry Burns), 1847-1930.; Kahn, Albert, 1869-1942.; Keating, Charles H.; Kelsey, Francis W. (Francis Willey), 1858-; Koch, Theodore Wesley, 1871-1941.; Little, Clarence C. (Clarence Cook), 1888-; McAllister, Samuel Wilson, 1890-; MacLeish, Archibald, 1892-1982.; McClure, Grace, 1884-; Mercati, Giovanni, 1866-1957.; Muller, Robert H.; Newberry, Truman Handy, 1864-1945.; Osborn, Chase S. (Chase Salmon), 1860-; Osborn, Stellanova, 1894-1988.; Power, Eugene B., 1905-; Purdy, G. Flint (George Flint), 1905-1969.; Putnam, Herbert, 1861-1955.; Rice, Warner Grenelle, 1899-; Riggs, Donald E.; Robbins, Frank Egleston, 1884-; Rowe, Leo S., 1871-1946.; Ruthven, Alexander Grant, 1882-1971.; Spaulding, Thomas M. (Thomas Marshall), 1882-; Spencer, Mary Clare Wilson, 1842-1923.; Spill, William Ambrose, 1876-; Strohm, Adam Julius, 1870-; Ten Brook, Andrew, 1814-1899.; Tisserant, Eugène, 1884-1972.; Todd, Albert May, 1850-1931.; Ulveling, Ralph Adrian, 1902-; Utley, Henry Munson, 1836-1917.; Vandenberg, Arthur H. (Arthur Hendrick), 1884-1951.; Wagman, Frederick H.; Walton, Genevieve Maria Julia, 1857-; Warner, Robert M. (Robert Mark), 1927-2007.; White, William Allen, 1868-1944.; Wilson, Halsey William, 1868-1954.
- Director's Files, 1905-2013
  The Director's Office subgroup constitutes the largest portion of the Library record group. It is made of a Topical Files series which is divide into a number subseries reflecting the various accessions in which the records received. There is some overlap in the date coverage of the subseries and an annual Reports series.
  The Director's Office Files, 1980-2013 (bulk 1998-2005) continues the series from previous accessions. Records in this series span the tenures of Richard M. Dougherty, Robert M. Warner, Don E. Riggs, William A. Gosling, and Paul Courant. However, the majority of the records originate from William A. Gosling's term as Director and Dean of the University Library. The series is divided into two sub-series: Topical Files and Budget Files.
  - Topical Files, 1905-1999
    The Topical Files, 1905-1999 series consist of materials concerning official library business and the directors' professional activities and consulting work. Each subseries represents a separate accession of materials but when taken together they create a continuous file from 1905 to 1999. These series primarily consist of intra-university correspondence and correspondence with library donors, with other libraries around the world, with state and national library organizations, and with vendors.
    In each of the subseries, the alphabetical arrangement devised by the director's office has been retained, although there are inconsistencies in it. Researchers should note that government agencies and other organizations are arranged hierarchically (e.g. "U.S. Library of Congress" and "Michigan. University. Library-Staff"), but this rule is not always applied, and material related to the two examples given can also be found directly under "Library of Congress" and "Staff", respectively. Organizations which have changed their names are usually found under all successive names. Material concerning the University of Michigan Library can be found under "General Library," "Michigan. University. General Library," and "Michigan. University. Library."
    - 1905-1950
      The 1905-1959 subseries contains the office files of library directors Koch, Bishop, and Rice. Of particular note are those which document William Warner Bishop's work with the Boolean Library (boxes 6-7) and the Vatican Library (box 49).
      - Academia Nacional de Sciencias Antonio Alzate, 1934-1935 (Box 1)
      - Adelaide University, 1936-1941 (Box 1)
      - Affidavits, 1921-1937 (Box 1)
      - Agnes Scott College, 1933-1941 (Box 1)
      - Air Raid Precautions, 1941-1942 (Box 1)
      - Aiton, Arthur S., 1926-1927 (Box 1)
      - Albion College, 1917-1938 (Box 1)
      - Albion Public Library, 1920-1929 (Box 1)
      - Alexander Turnbull Library, 1936-1941 (Box 1)
      - Alger (General R.) Papers (Box 1)
      - Alien Property Custodian
        - 1943-1944 (Box 1)
        - 1944-1946 (Box 1)
      - All-India Library Conference, 1937-1938 (Box 1)
      - Allegheny College, 1931-1941 (Box 1)
      - Alma College, 1946-1947 (Box 1)
      - Alpha Delta Phi Fraternity, 1936-1939 (Box 1)
      - Altsheler, Brent, 1934-1935 (Box 1)
      - Alumni, University, 1927-1934 (Box 1)
      - American Academy, Rome, 1938-1941 (Box 1)
      - American Antiquarian Society, 1935-1947 (Box 1)
      - American Art Association, 1921-1922 (Box 1)
      - American Association for Adult Education
        - 1925-1931 (Box 1)
        - 1932-1938 (Box 1)
        - 1938-1941 (Box 1)
      - American Association for Junior Colleges, 1933-1941 (Box 1)
      - American Association of University Professors
        - 1931-1934 (Box 1)
        - 1942-1948 (Box 1)
      - American Book Centers for War Devastated Libraries
        - 1945-1948 (Box 1)
      - American Co-ordinating Committee for International Studies
        - 1937-1938 (Box 1)
      - American Council of Learned Societies
        - 1928-1933 (Box 1)
        - 1933-1934 (Box 1)
        - 1934-1935 (Box 1)
        - 1935-1936 (Box 1)
        - 1936-1937 (Box 1)
        - 1937-1942 (Box 1)
        - 1942-1946 (Box 1)
        - 1946-1947 (Box 1)
        - 1947-1948 (Box 1)
        - 1948-1949 (Box 1)
        - 1949-1950 (Box 1)
      - American Council on Education
        - 1934-1943 (Box 1)
        - 1943-1946 (Box 1)
        - 1946-1949 (Box 1)
        - 1949-1950 (Box 1)
      - American Documentation Institute, 1937-1938 (Box 1)
      - American Farm School, 1939-1940 (Box 1)
      - American Historical Association
        - 1925-1931 (Box 1)
        - 1947-1948 (Box 1)
      - American Library Association
        - 1933-1934 (Box 1)
        - 1934-1935 (Box 1)
        - 1935-1941 (Box 1)
        - 1941-1943 (Box 1)
        - 1943-1944 (Box 1)
        - 1944-1946 (Box 1)
        - 1946-1948 (Box 1)
        - 1948-1949 (Box 1)
      - American Library Association
        - Activities Committee, 1933-1934 (Box 1)
        - Adult Education Board, 1938-1939 (Box 1)
        - Board of Education for Librarianship
          - 1933 (Box 1)
          - 1934 (Box 1)
        - Board of Publications, 1928-1933 (Box 1)
        - Board on Library and Adult Education, 1927-1934 (Box 1)
        - Board on Personnel Administration, 1946-1949 (Box 1)
        - Board on Resources
          - 1941-1945 (Box 1)
          - 1947-1948 (Box 1)
        - Board on Salaries, Staff and Tenure
          - 1938-1939 (Box 2)
          - 1940-1941 (Box 2)
        - Board on the Library and Adult Education, 1934-1936 (Box 2)
        - Catalog Section
          - 1926-1933 (Box 2)
          - 1933-1934 (Box 2)
          - 1938-1939 (Box 2)
        - College and Reference Section
          - 1925-1932 (Box 2)
          - 1934-1938 (Box 2)
        - College and Reference Section Yearbook, 1928-1933 (Box 2)
        - College Library Advisory Board, 1931-1938 (Box 2)
        - Committee on Indexing and Abstracting, 1937-1938 (Box 2)
        - Committee on Aid to Libraries in War Areas, 1942-1943 (Box 2)
        - Committee on Annuities and Pensions, 1937-1938 (Box 2)
        - Committee on Bibliography
          - 1935-1946 (Box 2)
          - 1946-1948 (Box 2)
        - Committee on Boards and Committees, 1940-1941 (Box 2)
        - Committee on Book Buying
          - 1929-1934 (Box 2)
          - 1937 (Box 2)
        - Committee on Book Post, 1940-1941 (Box 2)
        - Committee on Classification of Library Personnel (Box 2)
        - Committee on Cooperative Cataloging, 1933-1937 (Box 2)
        - Committee on Fellowships and Scholarships, 1934-1941 (Box 2)
        - Committee on International Relations, 1936-1941 (Box 2)
        - Committee on International Cultural Relations, 1941-1942 (Box 2)
        - Committee on Librarian of Congress, 1937-1939 (Box 2)
        - Committee on Libraries and the War, 1941-1942 (Box 2)
        - Committee on Library Cooperation with Latin America
          - 1937-1941 (Box 2)
          - 1941-1944 (Box 2)
        - Committee on Library Technology, 1931-1933 (Box 2)